原视频名：What Happened In The Fog At Boca Chica - What Caused SpaceX's Latest Prototype To Explode
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/MoEv0dkWlvA
原视频发布日期：20210331
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Yesterday we got to see the culmination of the SN11 Starship test campaign.
昨天我们看到了Starship SN11测试活动的高潮
and well it didn't go according to plan.
但并没有按计划进行
Not even for the observers because it was incredibly foggy and we basically didn't see anything.
甚至对于储罐观察者们来说也是如此 因为当时雾气很大 我们基本上什么都没看到
We did have the official SpaceX feed but that kept on cutting out quite a bit.
我们确实能看到SpaceX官方的视频 但卡顿有点多
So I mean we heard the vehicle go up.
所以我是指 我们听到了火箭上升的声音
We saw some video from on-board.
我们看到了一些箭上相机拍下的视频
It got high around T+4:20. Hahaha.
它在T+4分20秒左右到达最高点 哈哈哈(棒读)
We actually get a quick snapshot from inside the propellant tank.
实际上 我们还看到了一个很短的推进剂储罐的内部镜头
This is the methane tank and you can see like the anti-slosh baffles along the side.
这是甲烷储罐 你可以看到边上的防溅板
There's a big pipe which is the downcomer from the LOX header tank.
还有一根连接液氧头部储罐的降液管
And you can actually see underneath it the spherical header tank which is used for the methane
你可以看到在它下面有一个装有甲烷的球形头部储罐
but yeah vehicle comes back down we see an engine relight and then we lose telemetry
但是 是的 在航天器往回下降时 我们看到一台发动机重新点燃 然后我们失去了遥测信号
and everybody else watching with their big cameras on site see an orange flag through the fog
而其他所有在现场用大相机的人 都看到了穿过雾气的橙色光芒
and some other tank watchers who had cameras set up very close to the launch site
而其他一些在发射场附近架设了相机的储罐观察者
start to see debris falling down around them.
开始看到周围有碎片掉落下来
In fact several cameras were knocked offline or knocked around.
事实上 有几台相机被碎片打掉了线 或者被打得七零八落
There was one obvious piece that I saw on the NASASpaceflight camera
我在NASASpaceflight相机上看到了一个很明显的碎片
which was very clearly a section of the skirt with a landing leg still attached.
这很显然是带有裙板的一段 甚至着陆腿还连在上面
大红袍子是一个梗，详见 youtu.be/egHxiX40eJY?t=25
So of course yeah I slept through all this and I woke up so I didn't even get the dressing gown.
那么当然是的 我睡过了这一切 而我醒了以后(才知道这些事) 所以我甚至还没来得及穿大红袍子
Now in fact I should be wearing it now right for this.
那么其实我现在应该穿上它才对
But yeah there's not much data to go on.
但是 是的 没有太多的数据来讲这件事
I mean seriously I don't know what we can try to get from this.
我的意思是 说真的 我不知道我们能从中得到什么
I was joking that maybe we could get everyone's audio feeds
我开玩笑说 也许我们可以使用每个人的音频流
and try to do like you know trilateration to figure out the altitude of whatever that's going on
并尝试做像三边测量那样的事情来确定那件事的高度
but yeah that would wait until I have enough spare time which will be never.
但是 是的 这得等我有足够的空闲时间 而这是不可能的
So we did get a little report from Elon who said that
那么我们确实从马一龙那里 得到一个小报告 他说
there was one engine which did not reach proper chamber pressure during the relight.
有一台发动机在重新点火时 其燃烧室没有达到合适的室压
But with the three engine relight that shouldn't have been needed
但在三台发动机重新点火的情况下 单发失效是不会有影响的
RUD = Rapid Unscheduled Disassembly(快速意外解体)
and yes an RUD happened a few seconds later.
而且是的 几秒钟后发生了RUD
Now on the onboard camera we actually see one engine light and then the feed stops.
那么 在箭载相机上 实际上我们看到了一台发动机点火了 然后画面停止了
But that doesn't mean the only one engine lit
但这并不意味着唯一的一台发动机点燃了
because there is a lag
因为视频画面有延迟
between the engine firing and the telemetry and video actually getting back and being decoded.
在发动机点火和遥测信号之间 以及视频数据传回和视频被解码之间 都存在着延迟
The best data we actually have is from photographs of the debris swarm laid out all over the place.
实际上 我们拥有的最好的数据是那些碎片的照片 而碎片到处都是
Head and shoulders above everyone else is RGV aerial photography who run their patreon
让我们来膜拜一下大佬RGV航拍吧 他们开了patreon
and I of course signed up because I wanted to see this site from above
当然 我注册了 因为我想从着陆场上空看看下方的情况
and you can see a very large debris field.
而你可以看到一个非常大的碎片场
Now most notably if you look close to the landing pad there's three pieces of debris
那么值得注意的是 如果你靠近着陆场看 会发现三块碎片
that they're very important markers to Starship RUDs.
这些对于Starship的RUD来说是非常重要的标志
They're the nose cone.
就是鼻锥(的碎片)
The nose cone has the flaps on and it has the header tank in it.
鼻锥上有翼面 里面有头部储罐
And more importantly it's not pressurized
更重要的是 它失压了
so when the rest of the tanks fail it tends to remain in one piece.
所以 当(失压的)储罐的其他部分毁坏的时候 往往会保持为一个整体
And that's seen pretty close to the pad to the northwest.
而这片残骸看上去在着陆场的西北角附近
There is the Raptors which are over to the west of the pad.
而猛禽发动机处在着陆场的西边
Those are sort of still very close together indicating that they probably landed together
这几个残骸都很接近 表明它们可能是一起落下的
and I also think I see the fuel header tank on the west side.
而我还觉得 我还看到了处在西边的燃料头部储罐
Now these three things are important because they're big and heavy
那么三样东西都很重要 因为它们又大又重
and so they probably didn't get pushed far away from where the initial explosion was.
所以这些碎片应该不会被远远推离最初发生爆炸的地方
They probably just fell straight down.
可能只是直直地落下
Now the rest of the debris field goes off like 500 meters, half a kilometer roughly to the north
那么剩下的残骸场就在往北大约半公里外
and to the west a little bit almost none to the south.
或者往西一点点 但南边几乎没有
This is a very odd dispersion pattern.
这是一个非常奇怪的散布方式
I'm not sure what triggered off.
我不知道这是什么原因引发的
But when you look at the debris it's all in very very small pieces
但你仔细看那些碎片 会发现都是非常非常小的碎片
which is kind of odd right.
对吧 这很怪
There's a few recognizable sections of the tank.
有几部分储罐是可以辨认出来的
But there's not like a big giant main tank section that we saw with some other RUDs.
但并不像我们在其他RUD上看到的那样 残骸中存在一个巨大的主储罐部分
So how could this happen.
那么这是咋回事儿呢？
Well I have a problem figuring this out
我有个问题想不通
because if you imagine that the problem is with the Raptors
因为如果你认为问题出在猛禽身上的话
and during ignition we have some catastrophic failure on those engines in the explode.
而在点火过程中 这些发动机发生了一些灾难性的故障 然后爆炸
Well logically that would affect the bottom of the thrust puck
好吧 从逻辑上讲 这将影响推力圆盘的底部
which might damage the bottom of the oxygen bulkhead
可能会损坏液氧储罐隔板的底部
and we've seen failures of that or oxygen bulkhead before.
而我们以前也看到过液氧储罐隔板的故障
We saw that on SN1 if you remember and we saw that on SN10.
如果你还记得的话 我们在SN1和SN10上都看到过
And in both those cases what happens is
在这两种情况下 发生的情况是
the propellant in there just gets squished out by the pressure and the vehicle moves upwards.
里面的推进剂被压力挤出来 航天器就会向上移动
In the case of SN10 the methane bulkhead failed moments afterwards and the whole thing took off
在SN10的案例中 甲烷储罐隔板瞬间就损坏了 然后整个部分都飞走了
but importantly the tank just sort of squishes down.
但重要的是储罐(隔板)就这样被挤下来了
And is pretty much intact until it hit the ground.
而且(航天器的其他部分)在落地之前几乎是完好无损的
And so that's not what happened here because we actually see the debris spread out.
那么这不是这次所发生的事情 因为我们实际上看到碎片散开了
That means the tank actually exploded all the way up the side
这意味着储罐实际上是从侧面炸开的
and like when you have a pressure failure on a tank it sort of tends to start with a crack
而这就像在储罐上出现失压故障时 它往往会从裂缝开始
and then that crack will propagate and spread out
然后裂缝就会蔓延开来
but it's sort of limited by how far it can proceed
但这样的发展仍然是受限制的
because as it starts to crack pressure starts to drop
因为当它开始裂开时 压力开始下降
so I don't tend to see tanks like this.
所以 我不认为储罐上发生了这样的事情
That break up into so many small pieces from just a pressure failure.
导致其碎裂成这么多的小块 而仅仅是因为失压故障
I mean it does happen.
我是指 确实发生了失压
It's not unknown.
并不是没有发生过
But given the history we've seen with the Starships.
但从Starship(测试)的历史来看
The ones that have shattered into lots of pieces have been
碎裂成许多碎片的情况都是
they've hit the ground and then shattered right.
撞到地面以后发生的破碎 对吧
And that's where you've got load being applied to them in various ways.
而这样的话 施加在其上的负荷是不一样的
So this looks to me like the tanks were like exploded from the inside.
那么在我看来 这些储罐就像是从内部爆炸了
now if I'd looked at this I would have said
那么之前如果我这样研究后 我会这么说
well that really looks like the flight termination system was triggered.
看起来真的像是飞行终止系统(FTS)被触发了
Intentionally tried to break the thing up into lots of pieces
这样 是有意要把这东西分成很多块的
but there are plenty of sources who are familiar with individuals at SpaceX
但有很多与SpaceX的人员很熟的消息来源表明
who assure me and assure the world that flight termination system was not triggered.
他们保证飞行终止系统没有被触发
Now this does have an automatic flight termination system.
那么 Starship SN11确实配备有一个自动飞行终止系统
Maybe it happened before telemetry.
也许系统启动于遥测数据传回之前
I don't know.
我不知道
I think they would know so I'm going to trust them that the FTS didn't fire.
我想他们会知道这到底咋回事的 那么我相信他们的说法 FTS没有被触发
but maybe there'll be some clues that show otherwise.
但也许会有一些线索表明不是这样的
So then that leaves a possible explosion inside the tanks
如果这样 那就只有储罐内部可能发生爆炸了
that something starts to happen moments after ignition.
在点火后的瞬间 一些事情开始发生
Maybe during the flight there was some mixing of methane and liquid oxygen
也许在飞行过程中 甲烷和液氧发生了一部分储罐混合
and during the relight something happened that then caused the combustion to happen.
而在重新点火的过程中 发生了一些事情 导致了燃烧的发生
And then you basically have a very rapid pressure increase inside the tanks.
然后 基本上 在储罐内部 压力非常快速地增加
and that causes your mixing
而这就导致了混合
and can of course cause the tanks to be torn apart very very quickly into small pieces.
当然也会导致储罐被非常非常快地撕裂成小块
That's what I'm thinking but I don't know.
我是这么想的 但我不清楚
It is a conundrum to be sure and I'm not sure we'll ever know it.
这肯定是一个难题 我不确定我们是否会搞清楚它
SN11 boy that was a that's an interesting yeah I don't know.
SN11 兄啊 这很有趣 但我搞不清楚
There's debris everywhere.
到处都是碎片
Isla Blanca Park距离着陆场大概8公里左右
Now there is a piece of debris that was found a couple of miles to the north.
那么有一块碎片在北边几公里的地方被发现了
And that's a very lightweight piece of insulation
那是一块很轻的隔热材料
that must have fallen off when they were altitude and sort of blown down that way.
那肯定是在一定高度的情况下掉落的 然后被风吹到那里了
Also by the way the event was big enough to show up on weather radar.
另外顺便说一下 这个事件影响很大 足以在天气雷达上显示出来
We see it just floating off into the distance.
我们看到它漂到了远处
So yeah we know that it must have exploded in flight right.
那么是的 我们知道它一定是在飞行中爆炸了 对吧
It couldn't have hit the ground and exploded further.
它不可能是撞到地面上再爆炸的
We know that the tank came apart in multiple pieces.
我们知道 储罐解体成好多块
It was pretty energetic.
它的能量相当大
We're told that the flight termination system didn't happen okay.
我们被告知 飞行终止系统并没有被激活 好吧
So next things to look forward to is that well booster one has been given some small tests
所以接下来值得期待的是 Super Heavy BN1已经进行了一些小规模的测试
but it sounds like they're already thinking about when they're gonna you know dismantle it.
但听起来他们已经在考虑什么时候要把它拆掉了
Because they really don't have a test stand ready for it.
因为他们真的没有准备好测试台
And the next prototype that is up is serial number 15
而下一台原型机是SN15
and serial number 15 is big redesign.
而SN15进行了较大的重新设计
It's gonna look pretty similar on the outside for sure.
它的外观肯定会很相似
But internally they've done a lot of reworking a lot of changes to various pieces of hardware.
但在内部 已经对很多设备做了很多的修改
It's all super secret but we're told it's the new secret sauce.
这都是超级机密的 但我们被告知这是新的秘方
and this one will work for sure.
而且肯定能起作用
It also is going to feature a new generation of Raptor engines
它还将采用新一代的猛禽发动机
because well there's of course been concerns about how reliable the Raptors are
因为猛禽发动机的可靠性一直备受关注
given that they're very complicated engines
鉴于它们是非常复杂的发动机
and we all know that Elon famously said that the best part is no party.
而我们都知道 马一龙有句名言 最好的零件是没有零件
Dislikes complexity.
复杂的东西 坏
And yet the Raptors are the most complicated rocket engines ever built.
然而猛禽发动机是有史以来最复杂的火箭发动机
But that is in the name of reliability and reusability.
但这是为了可靠性和可重复使用而开发的
So anyway new generation of Raptors may solve a number of problems we're seeing.
那么不管怎么说 新一代猛禽发动机可能会解决我们看到的一些问题
But boy that I don't know this feels like a real setback.
但是 兄啊 我不知道(这是否可靠) 这感觉真的是一个挫折
youtu.be/-JmUVc8sLjw
Now I guess I'm off to make a dear moon video
那么我想我要去做一个关于亲爱的月球 的视频了
hoping that I'll fly around the moon in one of these things someday.
(通过这个视频)希望有一天我会搭乘其中一艘Starship绕飞月球
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]